Guide to the Hartmann collection on Indochina, [ca. 1900-1970]
Hartmann collection on Indochina, [ca. 1900-1970]
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Hartmann collection on Indochina, [ca. 1900-1970]
4298
Paul Hartmann
7.5 cubic ft.
Photographs, illustrations from books and magazines, and a few printed articles.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The Hartmann Collection's main focus is Vietnam, but there is material on Cambodia and Laos, as well as a few items on Burma and Thailand. There are numerous scenes of all parts of Indochina, with particular attention to various important architectural sites. Historical materials emphasize the colonial period. Of particular interest are an extensive collection of portraits of Vietnamese and Cambodian monarchs from the colonial period and a wide and (generally) well-labelled selection of pictures showing the many different ethnic groups in Vietnam.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The Hartmann Collection is a compilation of photographs, illustrations from books and magazines, and a few printed articles. The main focus of the collection is Vietnam, but there is material on Cambodia and Laos, as well as a few items on Burma and Thailand. There are numerous scenes of all parts of Indochina, with particular attention to various important architectural sites (in Hue and Angkor, for example) and to the Saigon area. Included are pictures of various stores and factories in South Vietnam during the post-1954 period. Historical materials emphasize the colonial period; there are a number of illustrations taken from books and periodicals about the colonization of Vietnam and Cambodia by the French in the 19th century. Numerous photographs of individuals can be found; of particular interest are an extensive collection of portraits of Vietnamese and Cambodian monarchs from the colonial period and a wide and (generally) well-labelled selection of pictures showing the many different ethnic groups in Vietnam. There are a considerable number of maps, especially numerous are road maps, including some produced by the Vietnamese government, and street/tourist guides to Saigon. Also, catalogs of Hartmann's collections.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Hartmann, Paul.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Vietnam.; Architecture--Asia, Southeastern.; Architecture--Vietnam.; Architecture--Cambodia.; Art, Southeast Asian.; Art--Cambodia.; Art, Vietnamese.; Caodaism.; Cham (Southeast Asian people); Ethnology--Vietnam.; Ethnology--Indochina.; Minorities--Vietnam.; Monarchy--Vietnam.; Monarchy--Cambodia.
Places:
Vietnam--Description and travel.; Cambodia--Description and travel.; Laos--Description and travel.; Burma--Description and travel.; Thailand--Description and travel.; Vietnam--History--19th century.; Vietnam--History--20th century.; Vietnam--Maps.; Cambodia--Maps.; France--Colonies--Asia.
Form and Genre Terms:
Maps.; Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. History
Box 1-2
Series II. Archaeology
Box 2
Series III. Maps
Box 2
Series IV. Geography
Box 3
Series V. Architecture
Box 3-4
Series VI. Art
Box 4
Series VII. Performing Arts
Box 5
Series VIII. Religion and Rituals
Box 5
Series IX. Ethnology
Box 5
Series X. Agriculture
Box 6
Series XI. Industry
Box 6
Series XII. Commerce
Box 6
Series XIII. Transportation
Box 6
Series XIV. Education
Box 6
Series XV. Miscellaneous
Box 7-8
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. History
  - Indochina, List of historical monunments (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Vietnam, Miscellaneous articles (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Vietnam, Pre-nineteenth century (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Vietnam, Travellers and explorers (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Vietnam, Nguyen Dynasty (pre-conquest) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Vietnam, Catholicism (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Vietnam, French conquest - Cochin China (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Vietnam, French conquest - Annam (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Vietnam, French conquest - Tonkin (Box 1, Folder 9-12)
  - Vietnam, Colonial period - Monarchs (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Vietnam, Colonial period - Officials (Vietnamese) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Vietnam, Colonial period - Prominent Vietnamese (not officials) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Vietnam, Colonial period - French administrators (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Vietnam, Colonial period - Prominent Frenchmen (not officials) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Vietnam, Colonial period - Views - Hanoi (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Vietnam, Colonial period - Views - Tonkin (excluding Hanoi) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Vietnam, Colonial period - Views - Annam (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Vietnam, Colonial period - Views - Cochin China (excluding Saigon) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Vietnam, Colonial period - Education and health (Box 1, Folder 22-24)
  - Vietnam, 1940-1954 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Vietnam, Post-1954 - Views (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Vietnam, Post-1954 - Articles (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Cambodia, Conquest and colonial period (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Cambodia, Colonial period - Monarchs and officials (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Cambodia, Colonial period - Education (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Cambodia, Post-1954 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Laos, Conquest and colonial period (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Burman, Siam, Singapore, History (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series II. Archaeology
  - Vietnam, Stone (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Vietnam, Bronze drums (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Vietnam, Bronze (excluding drums) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Vietnam, Other materials (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Series III. Maps
  - Asia, Maps (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Southeast Asia, Maps (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Indochina, Physical and geographical (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Indochina, Historical and archaeological (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Indochina, Agriculture and natural resources (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Indochina, Economy, communications, and transportation. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Funan and Champa, Maps (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Cambodia, Maps (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Laos, Maps (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Vietnam, Pre-independence (through the tenth century). (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Vietnam, Tenth to fifteenth centuries (Ngo, Ly, Tran Dynasties) (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Vietnam, Fifteenth to eighteenth centuries (Le Dynasty) (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Vietnam, Eighteenth to Nineteenth centuries (Tayso'n and Nguyen Dynasties to the French invasion) (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Vietnam, French colonization (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Vietnam, First and second Indochina wars (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Vietnam, Road Maps (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Vietnam, Administration, population, etc. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Vietnam, Agriculture and natural resources (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Vietnam, Geography, climate, etc. (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Vietnam, Ethnolinguistic (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Vietnam, Commerce, industry, and communications. (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Vietnam, Northern region (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Vietnam, Central region - General (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Vietnam, Central region - Road maps (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Vietnam, Southern Region (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Vietnam, Cities - Northern region (excluding Hanoi) (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Vietnam, Cities - Hanoi (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Vietnam, Cities - Central region (excluding Hue) (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Vietnam, Cities - Hue (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Vietnam, Cities - Southern region (excluding Saigon) (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Vietnam, Cities - Saigon - Historical (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Vietnam, Cities - Saigon - Street maps and guides (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Vietnam, Cities - Saigon- General (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Series IV. Geography
  - Cambodia, Rural (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Cambodia, Phenom Penn (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Laos, Geography (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Vietnam, Northern - Hanoi (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Vietnam, Northern - Cities (excluding Hanoi) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Vietnam, Northern - General (Box 3, Folder 6-8)
  - Vietnam, Central - Hue (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Vietnam, Central - Dalat (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Vietnam, Central - Other cities (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Vietnam, General (Box 3, Folder 12-14)
  - Vietnam, Southern - Saigon - General (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
  - Vietnam, Southern - Saigon - Government buildings and monuments (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Vietnam, Southern - Saigon - Outlying areas (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Vietnam, Southern - General (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
- Series V. Architecture
  - Cambodia, Angkor - Angkor Wat (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Cambodia, Angkor - Angkor Thom (including Bayon) (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Cambodia, Angkor - Other sections (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Cambodia, Other areas (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Champa, Quang Nam region (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Champa, Binh Dinh region (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Champa, Po Nagar (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Champa, Other areas (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Laos, Architecture (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Vietnam, Northern - General (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
  - Vietnam, Northern - Hanoi (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Vietnam, Ninh Phuc Temple (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Vietnam, Thai Phuong Temple (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Vietnam, Central - Thanh Hoa region (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Vietnam, Central - Hue - Imperial palaces (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Vietnam, Central - Hue - Royal tombs (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Vietnam, Central - Hue - Other sections (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Vietnam, Central - Other areas (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Vietnam, Southern (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Series VI. Art
  - Champa, Tra Kieu (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Champa, Quang Nam (except Tra Kieu) (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Champa, Other areas (identified) (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Champa, Other areas (unidentified) (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Cambodia, Angkor - Angkor Wat (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Cambodia, Angkor - Angkor Thom (including Bayon) (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Cambodia, Angkor - Other sections (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Cambodia, Other areas (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Cambodia, Artisanry (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Loas, Art (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Thailand and Burma, Art (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Vietnam, Ceramics (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Vietnam, wood; mother-of-pearl (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Vietnam, Painting; weaving (Box 4, Folder 30-31)
  - Vietnam, Woodwork (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Vietnam, Bronze and metal work (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Vietnam, Pottery and sculpture (contemporary) (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Vietnam, Lacquer ware (contemporary) (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Vietnam, Other crafts (contemporary) (Box 4, Folder 36)
- Series VII. Performing Arts
  - Vietnam, Music and ballet (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Vietnam, Theater arts (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Cambodia, Performing arts (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Laos, Performing arts (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Series VIII. Religion and Rituals
  - Cambodia, Religion and rituals (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Laos, Religion and rituals (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Vietnam, Christianity (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Vietnam, Buddhism (including Hao Hao) (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Vietnam, Caodaism (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Vietnam, Other religions (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Vietnam, Festivals (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Series IX. Ethnology
  - Cambodia, Khmers (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Cambodia, Minority groups (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Laos, Lao (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Minority groups (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Vietnam, Vietnamese- Northern (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Vietnam, Vietnamese - Central (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Vietnam, Vietnamese - Southern (Malays and Indians) (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Vietnam, Bahnar (central highlands) - Bahnar (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Vietnam, Bahnar (central highlands) - Jarai (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Vietnam, Bahnar (central highlands) - Cham (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Vietnam, Bahnar (central highlands) - Maa, Koho (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Vietnam, Bahnar (central highlands) - Mnong, Sedang (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Vietnam, Bahnar (central highlands) - Others (identified) (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Vietnam, Bahnar (central highlands) - Others (unidentified) (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Vietnam, Northern hills - Yao (Man) (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Vietnam, Northern hills - Miao (Meo) (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Vietnam, Northern hills - Thai (Tai) (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Others (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Series X. Agriculture
  - Cambodia, General (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Cambodia, Fishing (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Laos, Agriculture (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Vietnam, General (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Veitnam, Crops - Rice (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
  - Vietnam, Crops - Rubber (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Veitnam, Crops - Tea, coffee, areca, betel, palm, tobacco (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Vietnam, Crops - Coconut, fruits, vegetables (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Vietnam, Crops - Peanuts, pepper, soybeans, sugar cane (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Vietnam, Flowers (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Vietnam, Vegetation (forests/scenes) (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Vietnam, Trees (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Vietnam, Animal Husbandry (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Vietnam, Wild animals and hunting (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Vietnam, Silkworms (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Vietnam, Birds (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Vietnam, Nuoc Mam and salt (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Vietnam, Fishing - boats (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Vietnam, Fishing - General (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Vietnam, Irrigation - Methods (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Vietnam, Irrigation - Dikes and canals (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Series XI. Industry
  - Vietnam, Mining (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Vietnam, Energy (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Vietnam, Manufacturing - General (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Vietnam, Manufacturing - Consumer products (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Vietnam, Food and tobacco processing (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Artisanry and crafts (Box 6, Folder 28)
- Series IIX. Commerce
  - Vietnam, Markets and merchants (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Vietnam, Businesses - banks, insurance, etc. (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Vietnam, Service industries - hotels, restaurants, entertainment (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Vietnam, Stores (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Vietnam, Port of Saigon (Box 6, Folder 33)
- Series XIII. Transportation
  - Vietnam, Roads, railroads, bridges (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Vietnam, Water (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Vietnam, Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 36)
- Series XIV. Education
  - Vietnam, Primary and secondary (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Vietnam, Tertiary (Box 6, Folder 38)
- Series XV. Miscellaneous
  - Oversized prints, broadsides, and articles (Box 7)
  - Origional Catalogue of the Harmann collection (in French); French Cultural Mission to South Vietnam high school syllabi, 1967; Five family photographs (Box 8)
  - Plans (Map-case Folder 1)